"Are Environmental Toxins Lower
in Wild-Caught or Farmed Fish?"
Although the levels
of industrial pollutants,
like dioxins and PCBs,
continue to decline
in the food supply,
there is one dietary source
that still remains
a major threat: fish.
Everything eventually flows
into the sea.
Yes, we can get some dioxins
from eating horses,
but most of our exposure
comes from eating fish.
The U.S. Environmental
Protection Agency
puts the tolerable upper limit
of dioxin intake
per kilogram of body weight
at 0.7 picograms—
less than one trillionth
of a gram— per day.
So, we should get less than this
in our diet every day.
As you can see,
we're already skirting the max
by just consuming dairy,
and fish takes us
right over the top,
even at low levels
of consumption.
So, the adverse effects
of chemical contaminants
in seafood may counteract
the benefits
of any nutrients in fish.
So much so
that many dietary guidelines
recommend no more than
one serving a week of fish
and seafood to cut down
on exposure
to toxic pollutants.
But which is worse?
Wild-caught or farmed?
Take salmon for example.
Salmon had the highest toxic
equivalents of PCBs,
followed by canned tuna,
as well as the highest
neurotoxic equivalents of PCBs.
If you compare the levels
of PCBs in salmon
farmed in Maine and Canada,
versus salmon
wild-caught in Alaska,
versus organically farmed salmon
from Norway,
compared
to the wild-caught salmon,
the farmed salmon,
organic or otherwise,
had significantly higher
PCB levels.
This appears to extend
to other contaminants too.
Based on the testing
of literally tons
of salmon samples
from around the world,
for every toxin
the researchers tested,
the samples of farmed salmon
had higher levels than
did the wild-caught salmon—
higher levels of DDT and
these other banned pesticides.
Over 10 times more PCBs
in farmed salmon;
over 10 times more dioxins.
In order to not exceed
EPA safety levels,
we wouldn't want to eat
supermarket salmon
more than once every two weeks
in Denver or New Orleans,
more than once a month in LA,
Vancouver, DC, Seattle,
Chicago, or New York,
just once every two months
in Edinburgh, Paris,
London, Oslo, Boston,
San Francisco, or Toronto,
and just a few times a year
in Frankfurt, Germany.
We can track pollutants
from the ocean to the table,
and it's through the fish oil.
The fish oil used in the feed
for farmed fish
transfers pollutants
to the fish themselves,
and then the fish carries the
pollutants to human consumers.
So, yes, salmon has
the healthy omega-3 fatty acids,
but they also contain
high levels of toxic chemicals,
and not just the PCBs,
dioxins, and pesticides.
Farmed salmon test positive
for antibiotic residues,
higher levels of forever
chemicals, and flame retardants,
and also test positive for
endocrine disrupting compounds—
hormone disruptors like BPA.
Something you don't see
in samples of sea vegetables
like seaweed, presumably because
of their low fat content.
Farmed salmon may also
have higher levels of mercury
than wild-caught,
though the opposite may be
the case for farmed tuna.
Arsenic also goes both ways,
with more arsenic
in wild seabream
compared to farmed,
but less in wild seabass.
However, all the arsenic levels
were bad,
exceeding
cancer benchmark values
indicating a moderate risk of cancer
due to fish consumption.
Some analyses have
found dioxin and PCB levels
similar across the board,
but, in general,
you can think of aquaculture
fish as "farmed and dangerous"
compared to wild-caught
in terms of higher
levels of most pollutants.
So, that's why researchers
emphasize the importance
of labeling as a means
to help consumers
avoid unnecessary exposure
to highly contaminated fish.
Unfortunately,
mislabeling is rampant.
So, the farmed versus
wild-caught question
may be largely academic
given the extent
of seafood fraud
and mislabeling.
An investigation
by the New York Attorney General
found that consumers
who bought what was advertised
as "wild" salmon
actually often received
farm-raised salmon instead.
Up to 43 percent
of salmon tested
across the United States,
for example, were mislabeled,
most commonly passing off
farmed salmon as wild-caught.